## NIPUN SHRESTHA



I am a research-focussed epidemiologist and a trained medical doctor (Nepal) with exceptional track record relative to opportunity. My major areas of research interests are advanced epidemiological methods and next generation evidence synthesis approaches, such as prospective meta-analysis, and individual participant data meta-analysis. I am highly proficient in management of large observational/ trial datasets and advanced systematic review methodologies. I show a clear trajectory toward exceptional research program leadership. My FWCI is 2.02 (SciVal) i.e. my work is cited two times more than the average researcher in in my Faculty (Faculty of Medicine and Health). I am listed among the top 2% of researchers globally since 2022 in all fields of science, according to the Science-Wide Author Database of Standardized Citation Indicators, published annually by Elsevier. I have authored multiple systematic reviews, some of which have informed the development of international guidelines.



#### WORK EXPERIENCE

05/2022-01/2024

#### Postdoctoral Research Associate [1.0 FTE]

University of Sydney

Sydney, Australia

· Worked on methods development for novel evidence synthesis approaches, such as prospective meta-analysis, and individual participant data meta-analysis (IPD). I Was also a core team member in IPD meta-analyses projects such as the iCOMP collaboration, which examines cord management in preterm infants, and the TOPCHILD collaboration which focuses on early childhood obesity prevention.

06/2021-03/2022

#### Postdoctoral Research Associate [1.0 FTE]

University of Liverpool

♥ Liverpool, United Kingdom

· Worked on an ESRC Newton funded project for designing community based mental health intervention for older adults in Colombia.

09/2020

#### Research Associate [1.0 FTE]

Victoria University

• Melbourne, Australia

 Worked on systematic reviews related to exercise/sports and health outcomes.

01/2015-03/2016

#### Research Officer [1.0 FTE]

**HERD International** 

• Kathmandu, Nepal

· Worked on several projects including health facility readiness surveys and evaluation of national programs and policies.

03/2009 - 02/2011

#### Medical Officer [1.0 FTE]

Government of Nepal

• Kathmandu, Nepal

• Managed a rural primary health care center that had 10 staffs including paramedics and staff nurses) in Nawalparasi district Nepal.



#### **CONTACT INFO**

✓ drnipunsth@gmail.com

https://nipun-shrestha.github.io/Profile\_page/

**4** 0480176154

**(D)** 0000-0003-3542-8130

for more information, please contact me via email.

#### SKILLS

Experienced in data visualization, statistical analysis and statistical learning models.

Experienced in survey methods, qualitative studies and systematic reviews.

Skilled in R, STATA, NVIVO, EXCEL

This resume was made with the R package **pagedown**.

Last updated on 2024-07-08.



#### **EDUCATION**

08/2016-12/2020

10/2002-

10/2009

2016

2012

2016

2002

#### Doctor of Philosophy (PhD) Epidemiology

Victoria University

Melbourne, Australia

Thesis: Increasing physical activity and reducing sedentary behaviour in mental health professionals. https://bit.ly/3vMgZdd

Concentration: Epidemiology, Health promotion, Research methodology

RESEARCH HIGHLIGHTS

Master of Health Sciences in epidemiology 09/2012-10/2014

University of Eastern Finland

Kuopio, Finland

Thesis: Workplace interventions for reducing sitting at work

Concentration: Epidemiology, Health promotion, Research methodology

- 2405 cites (Google Scholar: GS), h-index: 24 and i10 index: 32

- Epidemiologist 3 year postdoc

first/corresponding author, 86%

- 42 publications, 15

in Q1 journals (SciVal)

- 2.02 Field-weighted citation index (SciVal)

**Bachelor of Medicine Bachelor of Surgery** 

Kathmandu University

• Kathmandu, Nepal

Concentration: Medicine, Surgery, Obstetrics and Gynaecology, **Paediatrics** 

## **NEWSPAPER HIGHLIGHTS**

**MEMBERSHIP** 

- Reducing sitting at work
- Running and risk of death

### ☐ SCHOLARSHIPS AND AWARDS

Victoria University

Victoria University International Postgraduate Research Scholarship Melbourne, Australia

· 200,000 AUD

Travel grant for attending Cochrane Colloquium

Cochrane Collaboration

Hyderabad, India

· 5,000 AUD

Travel grant for attending Cochrane Colloquium

Cochrane Collaboration

Seoul, South Korea

· 5.000 AUD

· 20,000 AUD

Government of Nepal MBBS Scholarship, 2002

Government of Nepal

• Kathmandu, Nepal

Use Epidemiologists (INTUE)

- International Network of Time-

- International Society of

Hypertension

- Several Cochrane groups

- Nepal Medical Council

# OTHER STUDY AND RESEARCH OPPORTUNITIES

2020	Workshop: Sytematic Review Cochrane Australia	♥ Melbourne, Australia
2020	<b>Workshop: Introduction to Clinical Epidemiology</b> Utrecht university	• Online
2020	<b>Workshop: Introduction to Prognostic Modelling</b> Utrecht university	• Online
2016	<b>Workshop: Compositional Data analysis</b> CSIRO	<b>♀</b> Perth, Australua
2016	<b>Workshop: Dual Energy x-ray absorptiometry</b> ANZ Bone Mineral Society	<b>♥</b> Melbourne, Australia
2013	<b>Internship</b> Cochrane Work	<b>♥</b> Kuopio, Finland



### ACADEMIC AND PROFESSIONAL ENGAGEMENT

- · Initiated and led several internal workshops on systematic reviews at Victoria University and University of Sydney.
- $\cdot$  Served as executive member of early career professional network at University of Sydney.
- · Supervised a Master of Public Health Student from University of Southern Denmark (thesis titled: Prevalence of diabetes mellitus among tuberculosis patients and its impact on treatment outcome in South Asian Region: a systematic review and meta-analysis)
- $\cdot$  Supervised a Master of Public Health Student from University of Sydney (thesis titled: Scalability of TOPCHILD trials)
- $\cdot$   $\,$  Established international collaborations: >70% of my publications have international co-authors.
- · Delivered oral presentation at several international conferences including Cochrane colloquium and International Society for Behavioral Nutrition and Physical Activity (ISBNPA).
- · Prepared a booklet on various strategies for increasing physical activity and reducing sedentary behaviour for International Network of Time-Use Epidemiologists (INTUE) which can be found at https://www.intue.org/wp-content/uploads/2021/10/Make-your-day-active-for-health-and-fun.pdf.



- PLos One
- Frontiers in Sports and Active Living



- Cochrane database of Systematic Reviews
- British Journal of Sports Medicine
- Plos One
- Scientific Reports
- BMC Public Health
- BMJ Open

## RESEARCH OUTPUT HIGHLIGHTS

- C=681, Altmetric=992, cited in 6 guidelines. I led a Cochrane systematic review (IF 8.4) on interventions for reducing sitting at work. It received a wide-reaching media attention nationally (e.g., ABC News) and internationally (e.g., Times magazine, The Guardian). It also formed the evidence base of Finnish Medical Society and World Health Organization guidelines for prevention and control of obesity. Led to 4 conference presentations >200 participants (e.g. Cochrane Colloquium Seoul), and invited webinar (Health evidence; McMaster university). Influenced subsequent design of intervention studies for reducing sitting at work.
- C=90, Altmetric=64, I led a BJSM (IF 18.6) systematic review on interventions for reducing sitting outside of work. Led to 1 conference presentation.
- C=211, Altmetric=3642, I provided the methodological support on a BJSM review (IF 18.6) on association of running and mortality.
- C=27, I was secretariat member of a large collaborative project (iCOMP) which led to two publications in Lancet (IF 168.9), One in seminars in Perinatology, 6 conference presentation and informed the updated guidelines on cord management in pre-term infants from International Liaison Committee On Resuscitation (ILCOR).
- · C=85, Altmetric=49, I provided methodological support and performed the statistical analysis for this Cochrane review (IF 8.4) on effect of standing or walking interventions on musculoskeletal symptoms in sedentary workers.
- · C=50, Altmetric=63, I provided methodological support for a Cochrane review (IF 8.4) on yoga intervention for urinary incontinence in women.



1. Professor Zeljko Pedisic

Institute for Health and Sport, Victoria University, Australia

Relationship: PhD supervisor

2. Dr Shiva Raj Mishra

Research Fellow, NHMRC clinical trials center, University of Sydney

≤ shiva.mishra@sydney.edu.au

Relationship: Collaborator on >20 Publications

3. Dr Lene Seidler

Senior Research Fellow, NHMRC clinical trials center, University of Sydney

■ lene.seidler@sydney.edu.au

Relationship: Postdoctoral supervisor at University of Sydney